<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Analyses on Core-cognition</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Analyses on Core-cognition</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 10:15:34 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/analyses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mass formatiopn</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/mass-formation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/mass-formation/</guid>
      <description>Mass formation from first principles In this presentation we derive the features of mass formation and the associated mass cognition from basic features of life. We do this from the theoretical perspective of core cognition: the hypothesized cognition shared by all of life.
Core cognition describes the basic requirements for the selection of situationally appropriate behavior. Selecting situationally appropriate behavior is what all living agents do, all the time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two half brains</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/two-half-brains/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 16:33:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/two-half-brains/</guid>
      <description>This is a slightly extended version of Example 1 of the usefulness of the concept of core cognition that we gave of in the application section called &amp;ldquo;Human Cognition from Life&amp;rdquo; in our 2015 paper called Cognition from Life (page 11). It develops a connection with Iain McGilchrist&amp;rsquo;s seminal work on the divide brain.
Two Attitudes Toward the World and Two Brain Hemispheres
In Learning Autonomy (Andringa et al., 2013) we observed that successful life span development is characterized by an ever-improving understanding of reality in combination with an urge (and proven ability) to improve and shape the Umwelt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-actualization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/self-actualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 14:42:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/self-actualization/</guid>
      <description>A deeper look at self-actualization: what is it and what is it not? Authors: Tjeerd C. Andringa
This paper is about the highest form of mental health attainable: self-actualization. It is not a repetition of what Maslow has said about the topic. Quite on the contrary; it is a more or less independent derivation of the concept of complete mental health and full mental development that validates all Maslow&amp;rsquo;s insights while providing a scientific foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bureaucracy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/bureaucracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 11:46:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/bureaucracy/</guid>
      <description>“This is an older text, but accessable text, that eventually developed into a paper called: “The Psychological Drivers of Bureaucracy: Protecting the Societal Goals of an Organization.” (Andringa, 2015) that develops the topic of bureacracy much deeper.
Bureaucracy as perfect manifestation of the coping mode. This text from 2013 foreshadows much of the main content of this site (at a moment where I was still unaware of the possibility of core cognition).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusive definitions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/inclusive-definitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 18:28:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/inclusive-definitions/</guid>
      <description>How can we define scientific concepts such that they are inclusive of all phenomena that pertain to the concept?
Improving definitions  What distinguishes the language of science from language as we ordinarily understand the word? … What science strives for is an utmost acuteness and clarity of concepts as regards their mutual relation and their correspondence to sensory data.
– Albert Einstein
 In the years from 1991 to 1999, I contributed to the design and development of an applied cognitive science department – what has now become the department of Artificial Intelligence at the University of Groningen (the Netherlands).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The adaptive cycle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/the-adaptive-cycle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 18:15:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/the-adaptive-cycle/</guid>
      <description>Mini lecture on origin of the adaptive cycle (a construct developed in ecology). This video played a role in the Systems View on Life course at the University of Groningen.
The adaptive cycle is a very useful conceptual tool. Note that we have flipped the horizontal axis (referred to as connecteness) compared to the normal presentation. In a core cognition framework connecteness refers to low viability (stasis compared to vibrancy).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
