<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>index on Core-cognition</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in index on Core-cognition</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 05:44:45 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>kruger-dunning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/kruger-dunning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 08:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/kruger-dunning/</guid>
      <description>In 1999, Justin Kruger and David Dunning wrote a paper called “Unskilled and Unaware of It: How Difficulties in Recognizing One’s Own Incompetence Lead to Inflated Self-Assessments”. They noted that “People tend to hold overly favorable views of their abilities in many social and intellectual domains”. Because of this they “reach erroneous conclusions and make unfortunate choices”. This makes sense: if you overestimate your abilities, at some point reality will prove you wrong and you will suffer unexpected and generally unfortunate consequences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realistic Expectations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/realistic-expectations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/realistic-expectations/</guid>
      <description>This video addresses some issues associated with whether we as individuals or society have a solid basis to engage with the world. And what some consequences are if we have not. This is associated with how we appraise the world. The societal example is the Media.
Successful interactions with the world require realistic expectations about the world.
  The role of realistic expectations
 If your expectations about the world are wrong: the world will prove you wrong and you will be faced with the consequences of your erroneous expect    Role of the media:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
