<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr Tjeerd Andringa on Core-cognition</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/authors/dr-tjeerd-andringa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dr Tjeerd Andringa on Core-cognition</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/authors/dr-tjeerd-andringa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mass formatiopn</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/mass-formation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/mass-formation/</guid>
      <description>Mass formation from first principles In this presentation we derive the features of mass formation and the associated mass cognition from basic features of life. We do this from the theoretical perspective of core cognition: the hypothesized cognition shared by all of life.
Core cognition describes the basic requirements for the selection of situationally appropriate behavior. Selecting situationally appropriate behavior is what all living agents do, all the time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to core cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/intro-to-core-cognition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 10:47:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/intro-to-core-cognition/</guid>
      <description>What is core cognition? Core Cognition is the cognition shared by all of life. Core Cognition describes the basic decision making structures that allowed living agents to grow a biosphere from small and fragile to extensive, robust, incredibly diverse, and highly efficient. Core cognition describes the processes of behavior selection for survival and thriving, which is something that is relevant for all of living individuals: from bacteria to humans. But cognition for flourishing – coping – is essentially different from the cognition for survival – co-creation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 - Life&#39;s defining properties</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/1-lifes-defining-properties/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 20:47:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/1-lifes-defining-properties/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This 4 section series is based on a recent paper (Andringa &amp;amp; Denham, 2021) in which we outline the basics of core cognition starting from the demands to being and remaining alive and maximizing viability of self and habitat. In it we derive core cognition and its two main modes, coping and co-creation, from first principles.
This page pertains to living agents in general.
With this text come two summary tables:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 - Coping and Co-creation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/2-coping-and-co-creation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 21:07:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/2-coping-and-co-creation/</guid>
      <description>Section 2 - Coping and co-creation This section addresses the quite different and complementary features of coping and co-creation. We need both, because successful coping maximizes time for co-creation. The complementarity of the two modes, as two separate ontologies that disagree on many aspects, might be the root of life’s resilience. Where resilience is defined as “the capacity of a system to absorb disturbance and reorganize while undergoing change so as to still retain essentially the same function, structure, identity, and feedbacks” (Walker et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two half brains</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/two-half-brains/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 16:33:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/two-half-brains/</guid>
      <description>This is a slightly extended version of Example 1 of the usefulness of the concept of core cognition that we gave of in the application section called &amp;ldquo;Human Cognition from Life&amp;rdquo; in our 2015 paper called Cognition from Life (page 11). It develops a connection with Iain McGilchrist&amp;rsquo;s seminal work on the divide brain.
Two Attitudes Toward the World and Two Brain Hemispheres
In Learning Autonomy (Andringa et al., 2013) we observed that successful life span development is characterized by an ever-improving understanding of reality in combination with an urge (and proven ability) to improve and shape the Umwelt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-actualization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/self-actualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 14:42:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/self-actualization/</guid>
      <description>A deeper look at self-actualization: what is it and what is it not? Authors: Tjeerd C. Andringa
This paper is about the highest form of mental health attainable: self-actualization. It is not a repetition of what Maslow has said about the topic. Quite on the contrary; it is a more or less independent derivation of the concept of complete mental health and full mental development that validates all Maslow&amp;rsquo;s insights while providing a scientific foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 - Identity as coping and co-creation (in)adequacy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/3-identity-as-coping-and-co-creation-in-adequacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 13:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/3-identity-as-coping-and-co-creation-in-adequacy/</guid>
      <description>Previously (Andringa, van den Bosch, &amp;amp; Wijermans, 2015) we have connected the existence of an individual’s unique identity to the self-maintenance of the living state. Here we develop the structure of identity in terms of coping and co-creation adequacy. This leads to an enriched understanding of the interplay between coping and co-creation, and it demonstrates that the conceptual language of core cognition is a productive lens for approaching a well-studied psychological phenomenon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bureaucracy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/bureaucracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 11:46:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/bureaucracy/</guid>
      <description>“This is an older text, but accessable text, that eventually developed into a paper called: “The Psychological Drivers of Bureaucracy: Protecting the Societal Goals of an Organization.” (Andringa, 2015) that develops the topic of bureacracy much deeper.
Bureaucracy as perfect manifestation of the coping mode. This text from 2013 foreshadows much of the main content of this site (at a moment where I was still unaware of the possibility of core cognition).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusive definitions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/inclusive-definitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 18:28:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/inclusive-definitions/</guid>
      <description>How can we define scientific concepts such that they are inclusive of all phenomena that pertain to the concept?
Improving definitions  What distinguishes the language of science from language as we ordinarily understand the word? … What science strives for is an utmost acuteness and clarity of concepts as regards their mutual relation and their correspondence to sensory data.
– Albert Einstein
 In the years from 1991 to 1999, I contributed to the design and development of an applied cognitive science department – what has now become the department of Artificial Intelligence at the University of Groningen (the Netherlands).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The adaptive cycle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/analyses/the-adaptive-cycle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 18:15:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/analyses/the-adaptive-cycle/</guid>
      <description>Mini lecture on origin of the adaptive cycle (a construct developed in ecology). This video played a role in the Systems View on Life course at the University of Groningen.
The adaptive cycle is a very useful conceptual tool. Note that we have flipped the horizontal axis (referred to as connecteness) compared to the normal presentation. In a core cognition framework connecteness refers to low viability (stasis compared to vibrancy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 - Two routes to general well being</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/4-two-routes-to-general-well-being/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/4-two-routes-to-general-well-being/</guid>
      <description>This section addresses two routes to social well-being. There are many routes to prospective well-being; in fact, all self-help literature and political, economic, or religious ideologies propose them. We have selected the “ontological security” framework and a recent formulation of “psychological safety” to represent very clear, actionable, and precisely-worded coping and co-creation alternative approaches to general well-being. In this section we will apply our core cognition framework as a metatheoretical lens to inspect the “theories” described below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 - Conclusions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/5-conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 09:04:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/5-conclusions/</guid>
      <description>In this (long) two-part paper we aimed to derive central aspects of cognition from first principles and called the resulting framework core cognition. We summarized many of its key terms in Table 1. We derived two separate forms of cognition; coping: for addressing pressing problems and, hence, aimed at its termination; and co-creation: aimed at optimizing everything in the context of everything else and aimed at its perpetuation. We claim that both strategies are essential; but it is the interplay of their strengths that, somewhat unexpectedly but logically, leads to the dominance of one of them: co-creation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Key Concepts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/6-key-concepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 06:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/6-key-concepts/</guid>
      <description>Text based on Andringa &amp;amp; Denham (2021a)
   | Concepts Core cognition key concepts with definition     Core Cognition The cognition shared by all of life   To live Self-maintaining being different from the environment   Death End of self-maintained difference from the environment   Need satisfaction Acquiring and executing the necessities (food and energy) for life (self-maintaining being different from the environment)   Agent “An autonomous organization that adaptively regulates its coupling with its environment and contributes to sustaining itself as a consequence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two contrasting ontologies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/7-two-contrasting-ontologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 09:28:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/7-two-contrasting-ontologies/</guid>
      <description>This is a table with two contrasting self-consistent ontologies that arise from the defining properties of coping and co-creation. It complements the key concept table Ideally the ontology of thriving dominates with continual focused contributions of the ontology of survival. But it is also possible that coping starts to dominate to the exclusion of the other ontology: a coping trap
    Ontology of survival (coping) Ontology of thriving (co-creation)      Languishing Low viability state as the outcome of a pattern of ineffective or misguided behaviors High viability state as the outcome of a pattern of broadly effective behaviors Flourishing   Threat: behavioral constraints Agent appraisal of viability threats, entailing a reduction of the set of context appropriate behavioral options to include only those that allow the agent to survive Agent appraisal of the absence of viability threats, allowing self-guided exploration of opportunities that enlarge the set of context appropriate behavioral options Safety: behavioral freedom   Problem A perceived threat to agent viability that activates a pressing need and hence motivates reactive behavior A perceived possibility to improve (agent or habitat) viability and hence motivates proactive behavior and the expression of novel behaviors Opportunity   Coping The reactive fallback mode of behavior aimed at protecting agent viability by ending problem states.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>References</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/references/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 10:10:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/references/</guid>
      <description>The combined references of the two articles (published in Psychology in Russia)
Adler, P. S., &amp;amp; Borys, B. (1996). Two types of bureaucracy: Enabling and coercive. Administrative Science Quarterly, 41(1), 61–89. https://doi.org/10.2307/2393986
Andreas, P., &amp;amp; Price, R. (2001). From War Fighting to Crime Fighting: Transforming the American National Security State. International Studies Review, 3(3), 31–52.
Andringa, T. C. (2015). The Psychological Drivers of Bureaucracy: Protecting the Societal Goals of an Organization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kruger-dunning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/kruger-dunning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 08:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/kruger-dunning/</guid>
      <description>In 1999, Justin Kruger and David Dunning wrote a paper called “Unskilled and Unaware of It: How Difficulties in Recognizing One’s Own Incompetence Lead to Inflated Self-Assessments”. They noted that “People tend to hold overly favorable views of their abilities in many social and intellectual domains”. Because of this they “reach erroneous conclusions and make unfortunate choices”. This makes sense: if you overestimate your abilities, at some point reality will prove you wrong and you will suffer unexpected and generally unfortunate consequences.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
