<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Identity on Core-cognition</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/identity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Identity on Core-cognition</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 13:06:12 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/identity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>3 - Identity as coping and co-creation (in)adequacy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/3-identity-as-coping-and-co-creation-in-adequacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 13:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/3-identity-as-coping-and-co-creation-in-adequacy/</guid>
      <description>Previously (Andringa, van den Bosch, &amp;amp; Wijermans, 2015) we have connected the existence of an individual’s unique identity to the self-maintenance of the living state. Here we develop the structure of identity in terms of coping and co-creation adequacy. This leads to an enriched understanding of the interplay between coping and co-creation, and it demonstrates that the conceptual language of core cognition is a productive lens for approaching a well-studied psychological phenomenon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 - Two routes to general well being</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/4-two-routes-to-general-well-being/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/4-two-routes-to-general-well-being/</guid>
      <description>This section addresses two routes to social well-being. There are many routes to prospective well-being; in fact, all self-help literature and political, economic, or religious ideologies propose them. We have selected the “ontological security” framework and a recent formulation of “psychological safety” to represent very clear, actionable, and precisely-worded coping and co-creation alternative approaches to general well-being. In this section we will apply our core cognition framework as a metatheoretical lens to inspect the “theories” described below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 - Conclusions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/basics/5-conclusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 09:04:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/basics/5-conclusions/</guid>
      <description>In this (long) two-part paper we aimed to derive central aspects of cognition from first principles and called the resulting framework core cognition. We summarized many of its key terms in Table 1. We derived two separate forms of cognition; coping: for addressing pressing problems and, hence, aimed at its termination; and co-creation: aimed at optimizing everything in the context of everything else and aimed at its perpetuation. We claim that both strategies are essential; but it is the interplay of their strengths that, somewhat unexpectedly but logically, leads to the dominance of one of them: co-creation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
